Guide to the William Marsh Rice business and estate ledgers, 1855-1965 UA 102
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William Marsh Rice business and estate ledgers
1855-1965
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice, William Marsh
UA 102
58 Linear Feet (58 boxes containing 171 ledgers)
The business records of William Marsh Rice comprise data on his personal investments, his estate records and those of the Institute: ledgers; journals; cash books; day books; check registers; tax records; bank statements; land surveys; payroll and student accounts; letters to and from Rice himself, family members, business associates, employees, and the administrators of his estate.
Biographical Note
William Marsh Rice was born in Springfield, Massachusetts on March 14, 1816. He was the third of ten children born to David and Patty Hall Rice. Little is known about Rice's childhood but records indicate that he worked for a while as a shopkeeper in Springfield before deciding to move to Texas in 1838.
Rice started out in business as a merchant in Houston, Texas. His first business partnership with a Barnabas Haskill was formed in 1840 but dissolved by 1842. In 1844 Rice became a commission and forwarding merchant in partnership with Ebenezer B. Nichols, a successful Houston businessman. By 1850 Rice's siblings began to follow him to Houston and assisted in his ventures. On June 29, 1850 Rice married Margaret Bremond whose father Paul was one of Rice's many business partners. In the census of 1860, Rice is listed as having $750,000 in real and personal property, making him one of the wealthiest men in Texas at the time.
At least 15 enslaved people were included as Rice's property in 1860. According to county deed records and newspaper advertisements, Rice purchased, sold, and accepted mortgages on enslaved people; he also attempted to recapture enslaved people who fled him. In addition to extending credit to slaveowners who leveraged enslaved people as collateral, Rice also bought and sold cotton as a substantial portion of his antebellum business. Rice served on a secession committee in Houston after the 1860 presidential election, and during the Civil War, Rice and his wife Margaret raised money for Confederate soldiers. On August 13, 1863, Margaret Rice died, possibly from cholera or yellow fever. Shortly after his wife's death, Rice went to Monterrey, Mexico and stayed there until August of 1865 when he returned to Houston. In Monterrey, Rice smuggled cotton and manufactured goods across the Texas-Mexico border. Later in the summer of 1865, he went to Massachusetts for business and did not return to Houston until 1866. On June 26, 1867 Rice married for a second time. His second wife was Julia Elizabeth Baldwin Brown, a widow and a daughter of Horace Baldwin, one of the early mayors of Houston. Elizabeth's sister Charlotte was the wife of William's younger brother Frederick.
Rice and his second wife moved to New Jersey to live with Rice's sister Charlotte and her family. Rice and his wife divided their time between New York City and New Jersey with occasional trips to Houston to oversee business. During one of the Rices' visits to Houston, he was approached by Cesar Maurice Lombardi, who was interested in building a high school in Houston. Rice had been interested in endowing an educational institute of some kind, having revised his will twice previously to include a school for needy boys, first in New Jersey, then in New York City. After the meeting with Lombardi, Rice decided to fund an institute of higher learning in Houston. On May 19, 1891 the charter for the William M. Rice Institute for the Advancement of Literature, Science and Art was incorporated in Austin, Texas. Captain James Addison Baker, William's brother Frederic, Houston businessmen Emanuel Raphael, Cesar Lombardi, James E. McAshan and Alfred S. Richardson were named as the first board of trustees.
In article two of the charter: "(t)he objects, intents, and purposes of this Institution are declared to be the establishment and maintenance, in the City of Houston, Texas, of a Public Library, and the maintenance of an Institution for the Advancement of Literature, Science, Art, Philosophy and Letters; the establishment and maintenance of a Polytechnic school; for procuring and maintaining scientific collections; collections of chemical and philosophical apparatus, mechanical and artistic models, drawings, pictures and statues; and for cultivating other means of instruction ..." The charter also required that the Institute only accept white students, which was changed in 1965. The institute was initially endowed with a promissory note for $200,000 to be paid upon Rice's death. Rice revised his will on September 26, 1896 and left the bulk of his estate to his namesake institute. During the battle over the estate two lawyers became involved with the proceedings and would end up greatly influencing the final results. Captain Baker, a trustee of the Rice Institute, served as William Rice's lawyer. Albert Patrick, the other lawyer, was hired by Orren Holt in 1898 to investigate the residency question in New York City. There Patrick met Charlie Jones, Rice's valet. The two spent a great deal of time together and slowly a plan was formed. At first it seemed that Patrick was only interested in the settlement of the contested will and was looking for any way to win. He convinced Jones, in the spring of 1900, to start poisoning Rice with mercury pills as a way to avoid a court battle. By the summer of 1900 Patrick came up with the idea to forge a will that left the majority of Rice's estate to himself and small sums to relatives and friends. The forged will was dated June 30, 1900.
On September 8, 1900 a hurricane struck the Gulf Coast and one of Rice's businesses, the Merchants and Planters Oil Company, suffered severe damage. The business manager telegraphed that they needed money for repairs and the sum was most of what Rice had available in his bank account. Patrick was worried at the loss of such a large sum of ready cash and he convinced Jones to use chloroform to kill Rice. On September 23, 1900 Rice was murdered by Jones. Patrick, in his haste to get hold of Rice's cash, tried to withdraw money from Rice's bank using a check forged by Jones right after Rice's death. The bank refused to honor the check since Patrick's name was spelled incorrectly. When calling to verify the check with Rice, the bank learned that he was dead. Since the circumstances were suspicious, the bank contacted Rice's Houston lawyer, Captain Baker.
When Baker arrived in New York City, he learned there had been a new will written up by Patrick. Baker was suspicious of the will since Rice had never notified him of any changes to the one Baker had drawn up on September 26, 1896. This suspicion led to a long and sensational trial where Patrick's version of the will was exposed as a forgery and the scheme to kill Rice was discovered. Patrick was found guilty of murder and forgery on March 26, 1902 and was sentenced to die in the electric chair. Jones, who confessed to his part of the events, ended up being released despite being the one who had actually committed the murder. Patrick's sentence was commuted to life imprisonment by the governor of New York, but eventually won a full pardon in 1912.
On February 6, 1902 Orren Holt settled the suit over Elizabeth's will for $200,000. After the trials and settlement, Captain Baker and the original Board of Trustees set about fulfilling Rice's dream to have an institute for higher learning in Houston, Texas. To guide them, the trustees chose as first president, a young mathematician and astronomer at Princeton University named Edgar Odell Lovett, who signed on as president in 1908. Lovett had earned doctorates both from the Universities of Virginia and Leipzig and had taught at Johns Hopkins, the University of Chicago, and Princeton, the most innovative American universities of the time. The trustees sent him on a worldwide tour of the "competition," where he interviewed faculty, inspected facilities, and developed an inspired vision of what might be accomplished on the plains of Texas with a blank-check charter, a generous endowment, and high ambitions. The goal was a university "of the highest grade" that kept "the standards up and the numbers down." Lovett shaped the university that Rice would become.
The Rice Institute opened on September 23, 1912, the anniversary of Mr. Rice's murder, with 77 students and a dozen faculty. An international academic festival celebrated the opening three weeks later, a spectacular event that brought Rice to the attention of the entire scholarly world. Four years later, at the initial commencement, 35 bachelor degrees and one master's degree were awarded, with the first doctorate conferred in 1918.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center and requires 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research. One box is restricted and identified in the finding aid. For more information about restricted material please contact woodson@rice.edu
Accruals
Additional materials are not expected for this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Items donated by Rice University administration in 1993.
Related Materials
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online at: https://scholarship.rice.edu/handle/1911/62306
Index Terms
Subjects
Cotton; Business
Document Types
business records
- Series I: Business and Estate Ledgers
  - Ledger; Old Business; William Marsh Rice; Rice Grocery Store Accounts, 1855-1856 (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Ledger; Old Business; William Marsh Rice, 1858-1859 (Box 2, Item 2)
  - Ledger; Old Business; William Marsh Rice, 1859-1862 (Box 3, Item 3)
  - Ledger; Old Business; William Marsh Rice, 1868-1876 (Box 4, Item 4)
  - Ledger; Old Business; William Marsh Rice, 1881-1886 (Box 4, Item 5)
  - Ledger; Old Business; William Marsh Rice, 1884 (Box 4, Item 6)
  - Letter Book; Legal Miscellany; William Marsh Rice, 1884-1897 (Box 4, Item 7)
  - Day Book; William Marsh Rice, 1885-1890 (Box 5, Item 8)
  - Ledger; William Marsh Rice, 1886-1891 (Box 5, Item 9)
  - Letter Book; William Marsh Rice and Frederick A. Rice [damaged], 1887-1906 (Box 6, Item 10)
  - Ledger; Taxes and Commissions; William Marsh Rice and Frederick A. Rice, 1891-1895 (Box 6, Item 11)
  - Account Statements; First National Bank, Houston; William Marsh Rice, 1897-1899 (Box 6, Item 12)
  - Account Statements; South Texas National Bank, Houston; William Marsh Rice [missing], 1897-1900 (Box 6, Item 13)
  - Town Lot Properties; Groesbeck, Kosse, Mexia, Bremond, Texas, c. 1850-1889 (Box 7, Item 14)
  - Records of Land Transactions, 1869-1880 (Box 7, Item 15)
  - Petty Bills Received; Town Lots and Collateral Notes; William Marsh Rice, Estate and Institute, 1869-1908 (Box 8, Item 16)
  - Petty Register B-1; Town Lots Notes; William Marsh Rice, Estate and Institute, 1896-1911 (Box 8, Item 17)
  - Journal; Town Lots; William Marsh Rice, Estate and Institute, 1869-1902 (Box 8, Item 18)
  - Petty Register B-2; Town Lots and Collateral Notes; William Marsh Rice, Estate and Institute, 1869-1923 (Box 8, Item 19)
  - Town Lots Properties; Thornton, Wortham, Rice, Calvert, Ferris, Palmer, Hutchins, Melissa, Van Alstyne, Texas, c. 1869-1879 (Box 9, Item 20)
  - Town Lots Properties; Giddings, Van Alstyne, Melissa, Rice, Richland, Wortham, Ennis, Palmer, Ferris, Texas, 1871-1893 (Box 9, Item 21)
  - Town Lots Properties; Bryan, Ennis, Elgin, Ledbetter, Paige, McDade, Hammond, Richland, Texas, 1872-1902 (Box 9, Item 22)
  - Town Lots Properties; Thornton, Wortham, Rice, Calvert, Ferris, Palmer, Hutchins, Melissa, Van Alstyne, Benchley, Texas, 1873-1907 (Box 9, Item 23)
  - Town Lots Properties; Elgin and Burton, Texas, 1877-1881 (Box 9, Item 24)
  - Town Lots Properties; Records of Land Transactions, 1881-1885 (Box 10, Item 25)
  - Day Book; Town Lots Properties, 1881-1890 (Box 10, Item 26)
  - Cash Book; Town Lots Properties, 1887-1889 (Box 10, Item 27)
  - Ledger; Town Lots Properties, 1896-1902 (Box 10, Item 28)
  - Town Lots Properties; Giddings, Hearne, Burton, Perry, Harrison, Texas, c. 1888-1908 (Box 11, Item 29)
  - Town Lots Properties; Frederick A. Rice Letter Book, 1890-1892 (Box 11, Item 30)
  - Journal; Town Lots Properties, 1890-1892 (Box 11, Item 31)
  - Records; Town Lots Properties, 1890-1896 (Box 11, Item 33)
  - Town Lots Properties; Letter Book of Frederick A. Rice as Trustee; v. 1 [fragile], 1894-1897 (Box 11, Item 34)
  - Town Lots Properties; Letter Book of Frederick A. Rice as Trustee; v. 2, 1896-1896 (Box 12, Item 35)
  - Town Lots Properties; Letter Book of Frederick A. Rice as Trustee; v. 3, 1894-1896 (Box 12, Item 36)
  - Cash Book; Town Lots Properties, 1894-1901 (Box 12, Item 37)
  - Town Lots Properties, 1895-1902 (Box 12, Item 38)
  - Town Lots Properties; Mexia, Texas, 1896 (Box 12, Item 39)
  - Town Lots Properties; Assessment Record, 1897 (Box 12, Item 40)
  - Journal; Town Lots Properties, 1890-1895 (Box 13, Item 32)
  - Cash Book; Town Co., 1902-1907 (Box 13, Item 41)
  - Sales; Town Co.; loose papers, 1906-1907 (Box 13, Item 41a)
  - Assessment Record; Town Lots Properties, c. 1901 (Box 14, Item 42)
  - Sales; Town Lots Properties; Rice Institute, 1902-1907 (Box 14, Item 43)
  - Leases; Town Lots Properties; Rice Institute, 1907-1927 (Box 14, Item 44)
  - Ledger; William Marsh Rice Real Estate, 1892-1893 (Box 15, Item 45)
  - Journal; William Marsh Rice Real Estate, 1892-1893 (Box 15, Item 46)
  - Petty Register 3; Town Lots Notes; Rice Institute, 1917-1942 (Box 16, Item 47)
  - Lumber Business; Letter Book I; Frederick A. Rice and Henry H. Lummis, 1901 (Box 16, Item 48)
  - Lumber Business; Letter Book III; Henry H. Lummis, 1902 (Box 16, Item 49)
  - Lumber Business; Letter Book VI; Henry H. Lummis, 1903-1904 (Box 16, Item 50)
  - Lumber Business; Letter Book of Frederick A. Rice and Henry H. Lummis, 1905 (Box 17, Item 51)
  - Lumber Business; Letter Book of Frederick A. Rice and Henry H. Lummis, 1905-1906 (Box 17, Item 52)
  - Lumber Business; Letter Book of Frederick A. Rice and Henry H. Lummis, 1906-1907 (Box 18, Item 53)
  - Lumber Business; Letter Book of Frederick A. Rice and Henry H. Lummis, 1908 (Box 18, Item 54)
  - Cash Book; Rice Land and Lumber Co., 1911-1918 (Box 19, Item 55)
  - Ledger; Rice Land and Lumber Co.; includes loose papers, 1911-1950 (Box 19, Item 56)
  - Journal; Rice Land and Lumber Co., 1911-1950 (Box 19, Item 57)
  - Cash Book; Rice Land and Lumber Co., 1912-1917 (Box 19, Item 58)
  - Journal; Rice Land and Lumber Co., 1917-1921 (Box 19, Item 59)
  - Cash Book; Rice Land and Lumber Co., 1917-1921 (Box 20, Item 60)
  - Press Copy Book; Rice Land and Lumber Co., 1911-1940 (Box 20, Item 61)
  - Journal; Sundries to various towns, 1895-1901 (Box 20, Item 62)
  - Taxes; Rice Estate; taxes paid by county, 1891-1905 (Box 20, Item 63)
  - Marlin, Texas, Properties; correspondence, receipts, deeds, 1892-1965 (Box 21, Item 64)
  - Ledger; Rice Estate Accounts, 1900-1901 (Box 21, Item 65)
  - Journal; Rice Estate; Arthur B. Cohn, agent, Oct.-Dec. 1900 (Box 21, Item 66)
  - Ledger; Rice Estate; Arthur B. Cohn, agent, 1900-1901 (Box 21, Item 67)
  - Journal; Rice Estate Rents, 1900-1902 (Box 21, Item 68)
  - Day Book; Rice Estate Rents; includes loose paper, 1900-1902 (Box 21, Item 69)
  - Accounts; Rice Estate; Arthur B. Cohn, agent, 1901-1902 (Box 22, Item 70)
  - Rice Estate Rents, Apr.-Sept. 1901 (Box 22, Item 71)
  - Cash Received; Rice Estate and Institute; Arthur B. Cohn, Agent; includes loose papers, Feb.-Dec. 1902 (Box 22, Item 73)
  - Cash Received; Rice Estate and Institute; Arthur B. Cohn, Agent, Jan. 1903-Apr. 1905 (Box 22, Item 75)
  - Accounts; Rice Estate and Institute; Arthur B. Cohn, Agent, May 1905-June 1907 (Box 22, Item 76)
  - Ledger; William Marsh Rice, Jr., and James A. Baker; Trustees, 1904-1907 (Box 22, Item 77)
  - Journal; William Marsh Rice, Jr., and James A. Baker; Trustees, 1904-1910 (Box 22, Item 78)
  - Checkbook; Rice Estate with Commercial National Bank, Houston, Jan. 1905-Oct. 1906 (Box 22, Item 79)
  - Stock Book; Southeast Texas Oil and Mineral Co., 1901 (Box 23, Item 80)
  - Bills Received; Rice Ranch [binding damaged], 1892-1896 (Box 23, Item 81)
  - Day Book A; Rice Ranch; includes loose papers, 1893-1895 (Box 23, Item 82)
  - Ledger C; Rice Ranch [binding damaged], 1894-1896 (Box 23, Item 83)
  - Journal B; Day Book; Rice Ranch, 1894-1896 (Box 23, Item 84)
  - Day Book C-3; Rice Ranch [binding damaged], 1896-1898 (Box 23, Item 86)
  - Accounts; Rice Ranch with First National Bank, Houston; includes loose papers, 1897-1900 (Box 23, Item 87)
  - blank ledger; discarded (Box 24, Item 88)
  - Day Book D; Rice Ranch, 1899-1900 (Box 24, Item 89)
  - Day Book; Rice Ranch; temporary administration, 1900-1901 (Box 24, Item 90)
  - Cash Book; Rice Ranch; Frederick A. Rice, 1901 (Box 24, Item 91)
  - Loose Papers of P. M. Granberry; Rice Ranch, 1898-1901 (Box 24, Item 92)
  - no description; duplicate of #89, 1899-1900 (Box 24, Item 93)
  - Ledger D; Rice Ranch with First National Bank, Houston, 1899-1900 (Box 24, Item 94)
  - Day Book; Rice Ranch [missing], 1900-1904 (Box 24, Item 95)
  - Cash Ledger; Rice Ranch [missing], 1901 (Box 24, Item 96)
  - Ledger; Houston Brick Works, 1884-1889 (Box 24, Item 97)
  - Ledger; Houston Brick Works, 1884-1892 (Box 24, Item 98)
  - Cash Book; Houston Brick Works; includes loose papers, 1896-1907 (Box 24, Item 99)
  - Account Statements; Houston Brick Works with South Texas National Bank, Houston, 1897-1900 (Box 24, Item 100)
  - Letters to and from William Marsh Rice; General Business [one loose letter to his sister Charlotte, June 30, 1900], Apr.-Sept. 1900 (Box 25, Item 101)
  - Letters to and from William Marsh Rice; General Business, Jan.-May 1900 (Box 25, Item 102)
  - Letters Received; William Marsh Rice; General Business [one loose letter dated May 1900], Aug.-Sept. 1900 (Box 25, Item 103)
  - Invoices; William Marsh Rice; General Business, June-July 1900 (Box 25, Item 104)
  - Letters Received; William Marsh Rice; General Business [missing], 1900 (Box 25, Item 105)
  - Letters to and from William Marsh Rice, Jr.; General Business, Jan.-Mar. 1900 (Box 25, Item 106)
  - Cash Book 1-A; Rice Institute; includes loose papers, 1892-1906 (Box 26, Item 108)
  - Journal; Petty Cash; Rice Institute, 1900-1902 (Box 26, Item 109)
  - Cash Book; Rice Institute [missing], 1906-1907 (Box 26, Item 110)
  - [no description] (Box 26, Item 111)
  - Ledger; Rice Institute; includes loose papers, 1891-1907 (Box 27, Item 120)
  - Ledger; Rice Institute, 1900-1901 (Box 27, Item 121)
  - Special Ledger; Rice Institute, 1906-1907 (Box 27, Item 122)
  - Securities Register; Rice Institute [two books], 1911-1917 (Box 28, Item 128)
  - Securities Record; Rice Institute with South Texas Commercial National Bank, 1944-1947 (Box 28, Item 129)
  - Bonds Received and Disposition; Rice Institute, 1924-1936 (Box 28, Item 130)
  - Journal; Rice Institute; includes loose paper re Houston Brick Works [see #99, Box 24 ], 1891-1907 (Box 28, Item 131)
  - Journal; Rice Institute, 1900-1901 (Box 28, Item 132)
  - Special Journal; Rice Institute, 1906-1907 (Box 28, Item 133)
  - Bank Deposit Books; Rice Institute with South Texas Commercial National Bank, [two books], City National Bank, South Texas National Bank, [two books], Guardian Trust Co., Union National Bank for Student Loan Fund, [see also Box 33], Houston Land and Trust Co., 1921-1951 (Box 29, Item 139)
  - Account Book #3; Rice Institute with South Texas National Bank, 1907-1912 (Box 29, Item 140)
  - Account Book #4; Rice Institute with South Texas Commercial National Bank, 1912-1916 (Box 29, Item 141)
  - Account Book #5; Rice Institute with South Texas Commercial National Bank, 1917-1923 (Box 29, Item 142)
  - Account Book #6; Rice Institute with South Texas Commercial National Bank, 1921-1928 (Box 29, Item 143)
  - Index to Ledger C; Rice Institute [ledger is #124, Box 46] (Box 29, Item 144)
  - Index to Ledger D; Rice Institute (Box 29, Item 145)
  - Index to Ledger E; Rice Institute (Box 29, Item 146)
  - Index to Ledger F; Rice Institute (Box 29, Item 147)
  - Index to Ledger G; Rice Institute (Box 29, Item 148)
  - Index to Ledger H; Rice Institute (Box 29, Item 149)
  - Single Entry Ledger; Loan to John S. Stewart; includes loose papers, 1907-1909 (Box 30, Item 150)
  - Register #2; Collateral on notes; Rice Institute; includes loose paper, 1920-1940 (Box 30, Item 151)
  - Loose Account Statements and Credits; Rice Institute, Nov. 1900-Jan. 1902 (Box 30, Item 152)
  - Estimate on Louisiana Lands; includes plats; Rice Institute, 1910 (Box 30, Item 153)
  - Field Notes; Pawnee, Oberlin, Merryville tracts in Calcasieu Parish, Louisiana; includes loose papers [two books], 1907 (Box 31, Item 158)
  - Hotel Register [Benart? see #162], 1914-1915 (Box 31, Item 159)
  - Letter Book; William Marsh Rice, Jr., 1903-1909 (Box 31, Item 160)
  - Letter Book; William Marsh Rice, Jr., 1934-1940 (Box 31, Item 161)
  - Day Book; Cash; Benart Hotel, 1915-1917 (Box 32, Item 162)
  - Salaries Payable #1; Rice Institute, 1908-1914 (Box 32, Item 163)
  - Salaries Payable #2; Rice Institute, 1912-1918 (Box 32, Item 164)
  - Salaries Payable #4; Rice Institute, 1921-1925 (Box 32, Item 165)
  - Salaries Payable #5; Rice Institute, 1925-1927 (Box 32, Item 166)
  - Salaries Payable #6; Rice Institute [unnumbered blank cash book labeled "A. No. 2 Wm. M. Rice Institute"], 1928-1929 (Box 32, Item 167)
  - Student Loan Fund; Rice Institute; includes loose papers, 1922-1928 (Box 33, Item 168)
  - Student Loan Fund; Rice Institute; includes loose papers, 1929-1934 (Box 33, Item 169)
  - Student Loan Fund; Rice Institute, 1934-1957 (Box 33, Item 170)
  - Student Loan Fund Account Book; Rice Institute; includes loose papers, 1921-1936 (Box 33, Item 171)
  - Report on Louisiana Lands; Rice Institute, 1907 (Box 34, Item 156)
  - Louisiana Lands Tax Rolls; Rice Institute [missing], 1909 (Box 34, Item 157)
  - Land Transfer Book; Rice Institute, 1906-1930 (Box 35, Item 155)
  - Securities Register #2; Rice Institute; includes separate index, May 1, 1929-Oct. 3, 1936 (Box 36, Item 126)
  - Securities Register #1; Rice Institute, Oct. 1, 1906-Apr. 24, 1929 (Box 37, Item 125)
  - Ledger B; Rice Institute, July 1, 1907-Apr. 30, 1913 (Box 38, Item 123)
  - Cash Book D-3; Rice Institute, Sept. 30, 1919-Dec. 13, 1920 (Box 39, Item 119)
  - Cash Book D-2; Rice Institute, May 1918-Sept. 1919 (Box 40, Item 118)
  - Cash Book D-1; Rice Institute, Apr. 1917-May 1918 (Box 41, Item 117)
  - Cash Book C-2; Rice Institute, Dec. 1, 1914-Mar. 3, 1916 (Box 42, Item 115)
  - Cash Book C-1; Rice Institute, June 1913-Nov. 1914 (Box 43, Item 114)
  - Houston Real Estate and Building Expenses; General Land Expenses, 1906-1939 (Box 44, Item 154)
  - Securities Register #3; Rice Institute, 1906-1940 (Box 45, Item 127)
  - Ledger C; Rice Institute [index is #144, Box 29], May 1, 1913-Apr. 20, 1917 (Box 46, Item 124)
  - Cash Book C-3; Rice Institute, Mar. 3, 1916-Apr. 18, 1917 (Box 47, Item 116)
  - Check and Deposit Register C; Rice Institute, Oct. 1916-Oct. 1921 (Box 48, Item 138)
  - Check and Deposit Register B; Rice Institute, July 1907-Sept. 1916 (Box 49, Item 137)
  - Journal D; Rice Institute, May 1917-Apr. 1921 (Box 50, Item 136)
  - Journal B; Rice Institute, July 1907-April 1913 (Box 51, Item 134)
  - Journal C; Rice Institute, May 1913-April 1917 (Box 51, Item 135)
  - Cash Book and Journal; Rice Estate, Dec. 1902-Oct. 1906 (Box 52, Item 72)
  - Accounts; Rice Estate, 1902-1904 (Box 53, Item 74)